

Curriculum Vitae for Ola Skavhaug

Personal information

Address: Aslakveien 31 E-mail: ola@xal.no

0753 Oslo Phone: 92612490 Born: 10 April Nationality: Norwegian

Summary

I am a skillful software developer, researcher, and project leader with 16 years professional experience. My main areas of technical expertise are mathematical and numerical software development, algorithm development, advanced scripting with modern scripting languages, parallel programming, software testing and deployment, library design, and scientific visualization.

In 2013, I founded Expert Analytics AS together with Åsmund Ødegård. Since then, my assignments have mostly involved writing simulation software in hydrology that combines flexibility and numerical efficiency, and building frameworks for novel analysis of the behavoir of the North European hydropower markets.

Technical skills

Frameworks Numpy, SciPy, Matplotlib, Bokeh, Flask, MPI, Swig, Boost, Stl, VTK,

FEniCS, PETSc, SLEPc, Diffpack

Languages Python, C, C++, Fortran, Javascript, Perl, Java, PHP, Bash, Tcl/Tk,

Matlab, LaTeX, HTML, XML

Tools Git, Mercurial, Subversion, CVS, Make, CMake, SCons, GCC,

Autoconf, Linux

Education

2004 Dr. Scient in Computer Science, The Faculty of Mathematics and Na-

tural Sciences, University of Oslo. Thesis' title: "Numerical Methods

and Software with Applications in Computational Finance".

1996 - 1998 Cand. Scient in Computer Science, Department of Informatics, Uni-

versity of Oslo.

Professional experience

2013	Consultant, Expert Analytics AS
2011 - 2013	Innovation manager, Simula Innovation AS
2010 - 2011	Senior Scientific Programmer, Kalkulo AS
2007 - 2010	Research Scientist and head of the computational middleware software
	activity at the Centre of Biomedical Computing (CBC) at Simula Re-
	search Laboratory
2005 - 2007	Research Scientist and head of the project Software for PDEs" at Si-
	mula Research Laboratory
2004 - 2005	IT-managet, Simula Research Laboratory
2004 –	System Administrator, Simula Research Laboratory
2004 - 2010	20% Associate Professor, Department of Informatics, University of
	Oslo
2001 - 2004	Ph.D. Student at Simula Research Laboratory
2000 - 2004	20% Teaching Position at the Department of Informatics, University
	of Oslo
2000 - 2001	Ph.D. student at the Department of Informatics, University of Oslo

Languages

English Fluent German Basic

Norwegin Mother tongue

Personal skills

Applied Analyze, develop and implement complex algorithms in applied scienmathematics ces, while balancing constraints like flexibility and efficiency. Short,

agile development cycles with discussions and feedback from problem

owners.

Management Motivate and lead experts and PhD students, define and implement

new projects, facilitate communication in informal surroundings to

break up the work day.

Some interests and hobbies

Gastronomical Beer brewing, cooking

Other Reading, traveling, trekking, expeditions

Physical Telemark skiing, running, biking, climbing, yoga

Extended descriptions of selected projects

Activity LTM Analysis Desktop for Statkraft Role Senior developer and architect

Staffing Two main developers, and several analysts

Description Analysts at Statkraft use the so called EMPS model to understand

the long term behaviour of the North European power market. Although the core of this system is still solid and provides insights, the tools and workflows associated with it is dated at best. To fix this, Statkraft has started a project, the LTM Application Platform, that augments the simulator with a powerful and flexible domain model written in a mixture of Python and C++. The platform both serves as a frontend to the analysts at Statkraft, enabling new ways of viewing results through domain specific transformations, and helps to manage the large amounts of data that is both used as input and produced as results by the EMPS simulator. My role in this project has been to define and implement the domain model together with the chief architect at Statkraft, and contribute to designe the architecture needed to meet the requirements on efficiency with regards to making the simulation results available to the analyst as soon as possible.

Tools Python, HDF5, Bokeh, Matplotlib, EMPS model, Microsoft HPC Suite

Activity SHyFT development

Role Senior developer and architect
Staffing Four developers, several hydrologists

Description Enki was an open source hydrological simulation platform developed by

SINTEF for Statkraft over a time period of several years. The original implementation, being a proof of concept type research code, was not suited for daily use in an operational setting due to limitations on scalability, design and performance. I was hired in a project to remedy this, and we quickly realized that we needed to reimplement everything from scratch and use the existing code base as a starting point for the algorithmic aspects. The resulting hydrological forcasting toolbox, named SHyFT, is currently operationalized and run daily at

Statkraft

Tools C++11, Stl, Swig, Boost, Python, Armadillo, dlib, yaml, Codeblocks

Activity mCASH backend development Role Senior Python Developer Staffing 12-15 Python developers Description

In this project, I have been working on most parts of the backend of a new mobile payment system. This includes financial transaction handling, the internal bank implementation, messages emitted through various protocols based on recipients, OpenID Connect scopes implementation and payment for these, web handlers for endpoints, and Datastore transaction in the Google app engine, all in Python. I have also rewritten the instrumentation test framework, that does real life scenario, black box testing of the core system. The development is test driven, with tests covering close to 100 percent of the code base, follows the Scrum agile method, and utilizes state-of-the-art technologies like Git for version control, Nose for testing, and Sphinx for documentation.

Tools

Python, Google app engine, Git, buildout, nose tests, Sphinx, webapp2, Jinja2, OAuthLib, JSON, html, javascript, jQuery, Pusher

Activity Role Staffing Computational Middleware, Center for Biomedical Computing Leader, scientist and software developer

3-4 scientists and developers

Description

As a project leader, I had the responsibility of the technical development, scientific achievements, the economy, and the personnel in the project. The project strongly emphasized the development of reliable, extensible and numerical efficient software components for solving scientific problems through simulations.